{"tossups": [{"question": "This man supervised the removal of the Cherokee from the southeastern U.S. before allowing John Ross to lead the relocation. This man ordered the execution of the Saint Patrick\u2019s Battalion for desertion and treason. Following victories at Veracruz, Cerro Gordo, and Contreras during a successful Mexican-American War campaign, this man ran for president as a Whig in 1852, losing to Franklin Pierce. For ten points, name this American general nicknamed \u201cOld Fuss and Feathers.\u201d", "answer": "Winfield<em><b> Scott</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. The Carlsbad Decree was enacted specifically to suppress calls for this event. One war started during this event featured the decisive Battle of Koniggratz and resulted in the annexation of Schleswig-Holstein. The Seven Weeks\u2019 War was fought during this event, which France recognized after Paris was captured by Prussia. For ten points, name this event, which was achieved through \u201cblood and iron\u201d and orchestrated by Otto von Bismarck.", "answer": "<em><b> Unification</b></em> of<em><b> Germany</b></em> (accept equivalents)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "By brandishing one of these objects, Blanca Canales violated a 1948 Gag Law during the 1950 Jayuya Uprising. An early version of this object was designed by Ramon Betances for the Lares rebellion. For three weeks in January, 2019, one of these objects was waved by Lin-Manuel Miranda after performances of Hamilton which helped to raise funds after Hurricane Maria. For ten points, name this patriotic object that flies over San Juan in an unincorporated territory of the U.S.", "answer": "<em><b> Flag</b></em> of<em><b> Puerto Rico</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The definitive history of this conflict is considered to be A Savage War of Peace by Alistair Horne. A national capital\u2019s library was burned to the ground after a massacre in Oran during this conflict. This conflict saw several bombings from the OAS, which opposed negotiations with Ahmed Ben Bella. Thousands of pied-noirs fled after this conflict, which ended with the signing of the Evian Accords. For ten points, name this conflict, after which a French colony gained independence.", "answer": "<em><b> Algerian War</b></em> of Independence (accept<em><b> Algerian Revolution</b></em> or The<em><b> War of 1 </b><b>November</b></em>; do not accept or prompt on \u201cAlgerian Civil War\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A ruler of this empire who built 102 hospitals was said to have \u201csuffered from the illnesses of his subjects more than from his own.\u201d Water sources in this empire included artificial barays and the Tonle Sap. This empire succeeded the Kingdom of Chenla and was founded by Jayavarman II. This empire built a temple meant to symbolize Mount Meru that served both Hindu and Buddhist traditions. For ten points, name this empire that built Angkor Wat in what is now Cambodia.", "answer": "<em><b> Khmer</b></em> Empire (accept<em><b> Angkor</b></em> Empire before mentioned, accept<em><b> Kambuja</b></em>desa)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This organization was led by the author of Where White Men Fear to Tread, Russell Means, during the seizing of the Mayflower II. Leonard Peltier, a member of this organization, was accused of killing FBI agents Jack Coler and Ronald Williams at Pine Ridge. Members of this organization took over the Bureau of Indian Affairs building in the culmination of the Trail of Broken Treaties. For ten points, name this Native American interest group that occupied Wounded Knee in 1973.", "answer": "<em><b> American Indian Movement</b></em> (accept<em><b> AIM</b></em> )", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A battle for this city led to the use of damaged Polish swords in coronation ceremonies after Boleslaw the Brave chipped his blade in this city. This city was governed by the \u201cPravda\u201d or \u201cJustice\u201d code of Yaroslav the Wise, under which it reached its height. The Rurik dynasty ruled a kingdom centered on this city. This city was converted to Christianity by one of its Grand Princes, Vladimir the Great. For ten points, name this capital of the first East Slavic state, the \u201cland of the Rus.\u201d", "answer": "<em><b> Kiev</b></em>, Ukraine", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Charles Dickens criticized this work as the product of \u201cvery feeble amateurs.\u201d Captions in this work are called its namesake tituli, which often feature tildas to indicate abbreviations. Leofwine and Gyrth are shown as fallen knights in this work, whose final remaining caption is the line \u201cAnd the English left fleeing.\u201d Bishop Odo likely commissioned, for ten points, what work that illustrates how Harold Godwinson lost England to the Norman, William the Conquerer, an 11th century embroidery?", "answer": "<em><b> Bayeux Tapestry</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man insinuated that the 1999 Moscow apartment bombings were a false flag attack in his book Blowing Up Russia. This man\u2019s wife, Marina, launched an inquest into his death that revealed it was likely planned by the FSB on the orders of Vladimir Putin. After this man, who is reputed to have coined the term \u201cmafia state,\u201d allegedly defected to MI6, he was poisoned after drinking from a polonium-infused teapot. For ten points, name this ex-Russian spy who was assassinated in 2006.", "answer": "Alexander<em><b> Litvinenko</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A man with this surname was created the first Viscount Brome. That man\u2019s youngest son with this surname, Williiam, was an admiral, known for his command of the Channel Fleet during the Napoleonic Wars. William\u2019s oldest brother with this surname oversaw creation of the \u201cPermanent Settlement\u201d that regulated revenues received from India and also served as military governor in Ireland. For ten points, give the surname of Charles, the British general who surrendered at Yorktown.", "answer": "<em><b> Cornwallis</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This kingdom\u2019s \u201cIron and Golden King\u201d lost this kingdom\u2019s Adriatic coastline and his life in the Battle of Marchfeld. That king, Ottokar II, is buried with many other kings of this region in St. Vitus Cathedral. A man who lost his sight while crusading in Lithuania was the first member of this kingdom\u2019s House of Luxembourg. In this kingdom Jan Zizka led a movement that was named after Jan Hus. For ten points, name this kingdom whose lands were centered in what is today the western portion of the Czech Republic.", "answer": "Kingdom of<em><b> Bohemia</b></em> (prompt on<em><b> Czech</b></em> kingdom)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man contacted Tom Kahn on the false belief that Kahn added a line to a speech referencing Sherman\u2019s March to the Sea. This man called for \u201cmaximum possible\u201d integration while leading a New York City school boycott. This Quaker was the head of the AFl-CIO\u2019s A. Philip Randolph Institute. Strom Thurmond called this man a \u201ccommunist, draft dodger, and homosexual.\u201d For ten points, name this civil rights activist who was the primary organizer of the 1963 March on Washington.", "answer": "Bayard<em><b> Rustin</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Archaeologist Rodney Young uncovered a tomb popularly associated with this man at the Great Tumulus. This man was instructed to bathe in the river Pactolus in order to undo a gift he had received. This man received his most famous attribute as a reward from Dionysus after this man cared for Silenus. This man voted in favor of Pan over Apollo for a music contest, causing him to grow the ears of an ass. For ten points, name this legendary king of Phrygia whose touch turned things to gold.", "answer": "<em><b> Midas</b></em>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One of this playwright\u2019s characters, Dikaiopolis, asks the immortal Amphitheus to negotiate a secret peace treaty. Cleisthenes [kly-sthen-eez] becomes an ambassador to a group of women celebrating the Thesmophoria in another play by this author, who depicted a personification of Peace arriving at a meeting between Spartan and Athenian delegates in a work that opens with a meeting of women. For ten points, name this Athenian comic playwright of The Clouds and Lysistrata.", "answer": "<em><b> Aristophanes</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "This man offered himself as a vassal to Alfonso V of Naples in exchange for military support in the Treaty of Gaeta. This man met with the Arianiti and Balsic families in a Venetian-controlled town to form the League of Lezhe. Under the command of this man, Kruje was repeatedly saved from capture by the forces of Mehmed II and Murad II. For ten points, name this Albanian national hero who opposed the Ottoman Empire in the 15th century.", "answer": "<em><b> Skanderbeg</b></em> (accept Gjergj (George or Georgius)<em><b> Kastrioti</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man served as Senator from Ohio after he was elected from a party for whom he coined the slogan \u201cFree men, free labor, free soil.\u201d In his role as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, this man oversaw the impeachment of Andrew Johnson, years after he had introduced America\u2019s first federal currency in another post. For ten points, name this man whose face is on the ten-thousand dollar bill, who served as Abraham Lincoln\u2019s Secretary of the Treasury.", "answer": "Salmon P(ortland)<em><b> Chase</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A council in this city codified the filioque clause into Western Christianity and was organized by Bishop Leander. That council also directed 23 anathemas against Arianism. Under the Emirate of (+) Cordoba, a revolt occurred in this city by Abd ar-Rahman, and this city was the location of the \u201cDay of the Ditch\u201d duing which Amrus committed a massacre. This city\u2019s Alcazar was besieged by (*)</b> Republican forces during the Spanish Civil War. For ten points, name this city, the former capital of the Visigoths and the current capital of Castilla-La Mancha, the capital of Spain under Charles V.", "answer": "<em><b> Toledo</b></em>, Spain", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This woman\u2019s parents founded the first free school in Oswego, New York, and she was the only woman in her class at Syracuse. This woman was an early advocate for dress reform, arguing that women\u2019s long skirts were (+) unhygienic. This woman was captured and arrested as a spy after helping a surgeon perform an amputation. Because the US Army would not issue her a commission, this woman was personally validated by (*) </b> Andrew Johnson after the war. For ten points, name this woman, the only female surgeon during the Civil War and the only woman ever to earn the Congressional Medal of Honor.", "answer": "Dr. Mary Edwards<em><b> Walker</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One of this composer\u2019s works was composed for the Houston Symphony and memorializes the 150th anniversary of Texas\u2019s declaration of independence from Mexico. This composer created a piece in the aftermath of 9/11 titled (+) On the Transmigration of Souls. This man composed an opera which features characters including Rambo and the wife of the title character, Marilyn. That opera chronicles the hijacking of the Achille Lauro, while his best known work features the aria \u201cI Am the (*) </b> Wife of Mao Tse-tung.\u201d For ten points, name this composer of The Death of Klinghoffer and Nixon in China.", "answer": "John Coolidge<em><b> Adams</b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This event led its country to proclaim September 1 as \u201cDisaster Prevention Day.\u201d To comply with the Washington Naval Treaty, a battleship was being (+) converted into a carrier when it was destroyed during this event. During this event, many people lost their lives in firestorms initially caused by cooking oil. After the destruction of the U.S. Embassy, Cyrus Woods was relocated to the (*)</b> Imperial Hotel, which withstood the force of this event. This event was centered at Izu Oshima and measured 7.9 on the Richter scale. For ten points, name this 1923 natural disaster in Japan.", "answer": "1923<em><b> Great Kanto earthquake</b></em> (prompt on \u201cTokyo earthquake\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Two members of this family established the city of Saxonburg in the area surrounding Pittsburgh. One member of this family was the first to manufacture wire rope in America, which he used to create the (+) Delaware Aqueduct. A structure designed by a member of this family relied on two pneumatic caissons as a foundation. A father and son from this family oversaw a fourteen year project to create a structure that linked (*) </b> Manhattan to an eastern borough. For ten points, name this German-American family whose members designed the Brooklyn Bridge.", "answer": "<em><b> Roebling</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>On the first day of this battle, the Congress and Cumberland were destroyed, and a frigate ran aground. On the second day of this battle, Samuel Dana Greene made the decision to protect the (+) Minnesota rather than to continue fighting. This battle ended when fragments of paint exploded in the eye of John Worden, temporarily blinding him. This battle took place near Sewell\u2019s Point and proved to be (*) </b> indecisive as its primary combatants were unable to breach one another\u2019s plating. For ten points, name this clash between the Merrimack and the Monitor, the first combat meeting of ironclads.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Hampton Roads</b></em> (accept Battle of<em><b> Ironclads</b></em> before mentioned, accept Battle of <em><b>Monitor and Merrimack</b></em> (or Virginia) in any order before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man was at odds with his younger contemporary, Xunzi, who thought that human nature is to be greedy and self-centered. This thinker explained the idea of the Four Beginnings, or (+) \u201cSprouts,\u201d by using the analogy of a child falling down a well to show the innate goodness of humanity. This man served as an advisor to the King of Qi during the Warring States Period. This thinker was the student of Zisi, the grandson of a man who (*) </b> founded a school during the Spring and Autumn Period to which this man adhered. Known as the\u201csecond sage,\u201d For ten points, name this Confucian philosopher.", "answer": "<em><b> Mencius</b></em> (accept<em><b> Mengzi</b></em>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>According to Procopius, the actions of this man only upset Honorius because he thought his favorite chicken had died. This man died while besieging Consenza but had legendarily pre-planned to have the River (+) Busento rerouted to cover his grave. This man\u2019s soldiers burned the Gardens of Sallust and ransacked the Mausoleum of Augustus. This non-Roman fought under (*)</b> Theodosius I at the Battle of the Frigidus and led several campaigns against Stilicho. For ten points, name this \u201cruler of all,\u201d the first king of the Visigoths who sacked Rome in 410.", "answer": "<em><b> Alaric</b></em> I", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>The book Going Down Jericho Road deals with an incident in this city that was prompted by the deaths of Robert Walker and Echol Cole. A speech given in this city claims that (+) \u201cLongevity has its place, but I\u2019m not concerned about that now.\u201d That speech in this city was given at the headquarters of the Church of God in Christ and quotes from the \u201cBattle Hymn of the Republic.\u201d The \u201cI\u2019ve (*)</b> Been to the Mountaintop\u201d speech was given in this city where James Earl Ray carried out his most notorious action. The Lorraine Motel can be found in, for ten points, what city where Martin Luther King, Jr. was assassinated?", "answer": "<em><b> Memphis</b></em>, Tennessee", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}